(英文)
OK 恭喜發財各位
希望各位豬年快樂
Happy New Year to all of you
It's the year of pig
We're gonna have wish you piggy
OK
So I'm gonna preach the sermon
I'm gonna share my message in Chinglish
How's that OK
講英文混中文
今年豬年
希望各位都能夠像豬一樣發財
OK
I wanna share a couple of images with you
我想和你分享兩張相片
第一張相片
有隻豬去找一個紋身的
那個紋身師就問他
想紋些什麼
Piggy, what kind of tattoo do you want?
那隻豬就說
I want to look rich
我想紋一些東西
令到人家看起來很有錢
Alright
如果你是那個紋身師
你會紋些什麼
What would you do if you were the artist?
What tattoo would you put on the pig?
That would make the pig look rich
Dollar sign OK
What else?
Yeah, this is what he did
You wanna be a piggy bank, right?
You wanna be a piggy bank
That you look rich
在新年的時候
我們常常祝福大家
我們說恭喜發財
What does it mean?
恭喜發財
What is it?
Wish you well, right?
Or have a lot of money
This is all kinds of blessings that we say to our friends, our families, our neighbors
In Chinese New Year
We want them, wish them well
Right? A lot of material prosperity
A lot of blessings
More money, more
Maybe bigger house
Bigger car
多些錢
多些
層樓大些,多些食物
I want to think about
How does God expects us to handle our blessings
We know that God is God of blessings
Material blessings is part of His blessings
神是一個很豐富,很多祝福的神
聖經是這樣說的
其實上帝給我們的祝福和供應
是有物質上的供應
物質上的,吃的東西,住的東西,我們享受的東西
This is all part of God's blessings to all of us
However, how do we do with it?
What do we do with it?
How do we handle them?
其實耶穌經常說錢、財富的教導
耶穌經常說錢
所以我們教會也會說錢
Jesus talks a lot about money and wealth
That's why we in the church, we also talk about it
Especially in year of pig
We all want to be piggy bank
So I want to share a very simple story
Told by Jesus
It has to do with our perspective on wealth and prosperity and blessings
這個故事我想今天和你分享
就是在路加福音第十二章
這裡耶穌講了一個很簡單的故事
就是和我們地上的祝福是有關係的
我先讀一讀
Gospel of Luke chapter 12
Starting from verse 13
Someone in the crowd said to Jesus
Teacher, tell my brother to divide the inheritance with me
Jesus replied, man, who appointed me as a judge or an operator between you?
Then the man said to, Jesus said to the disciples, said to them
Watch out, be on your guard against all kinds of greed
A man's life does not consist in abundance of his possessions
路加福音第十二章十三節
他說眾人之中有一個對耶穌說
他說夫子老師請你吩咐我的兄長和我分我的家產
分家產
耶穌說你這個人誰立我作你段氏的官
給你們分家產呢
於是對眾人說
你們要謹慎自守免去一切貪心
因為人的生命不在乎家道豐富
And the story continues
And Jesus told them this parable, this simple story
The ground, the field, the farmland of a certain rich man
produced a good harvest, a good crop
He thought to himself, what shall I do?
I have no place to store my crops or my harvest
Then he said, this is what I'll do
I will tear down my barns and build bigger ones
And there I will store all my grain and all my goods
And I will say to myself
You have plenty of good things laid up for many years
Take life easy, chill, eat, drink and be merry
But God said to him, you fool
This very night your life will be demanded from you
Then who will get what you have prepared for yourself?
This is how it will be with anyone who stores up treasures thanks for himself
but is not rich toward God
耶穌就用比喻對他們講
他說有一個財主田產豐富
自己心裏面思想說
我的田產沒有地方收藏,怎麼辦?
又說我要這樣辦
要將我的倉房拆了
另蓋更大的,在那裏好收藏我一切的糧食和財物
然後要對我的靈魂講
靈魂啊,你有許多的財物積存
可作多年的費用
只管安安日日地吃喝快樂吧
神卻對他說
無知的人啊,今夜必要你的靈魂
你所預備的要歸誰呢?
凡為自己積財,在神面前卻不富足
也是這樣
Very simple story, ok?
This story is called the parable of rich fool
叫做無知財主的比喻
這個故事很簡單
他有一個很有錢的人
他有很多錢,他越來越有錢
然後他就想,那我就可以安安日日
神就對他說
Guess what? Your time is up
And you don't even know it
Talking about rich man
你看看這個故事
你知道這個人沒有做錯任何事
你知道他田產豐富
This rich guy didn't do anything immoral
He got a good harvest
He got a good produce
Quantity earning exceed expectation
Exceed forecast
或者他可能去年做得很辛苦
Working really hard
這些是他值得有的東西
越來越多錢
他有個good year
他有個很好的回報
Most probably he work overtime I guess
And he deserve all this good things
All this blessing
And nothing immoral that he has done
沒有做過不道德的事
他值得得到這些
But what's wrong with the picture
Now, a surface of plain meaning of the story
Will have us believe
That Jesus is against all rich people
Jesus is against wealth
表面上看,你會覺得
耶穌或者聖經是很爭錢的
耶穌覺得人都要窮
有錢他就最憎
有錢他就要拿你的錢
But this is a very superficial understanding of the story
但不可以這樣去解
不可以說這個故事
就是說耶穌很憎我們有錢
我們有錢就是有罪
沒有這個意思
You have to remember
This story was told in a Jewish context
A Jewish culture
We all know in the Jewish society
Financial management, financial gain, material blessing
Is the backbone of Jewish culture
All the Jews, most of the Jews are rich I think
Many of the Jews
Although there are many poor Jews in the world
但我們知道這個故事
是說這個故事的時候
是對猶太人的文化,猶太人的社會說的
我們都知道很多猶太人都有錢
猶太人很會做生意
耶穌就是跟這個背景
跟這些人來說話
而我們知道猶太人的文化
管錢,賺錢
是他們文化的軸心
是他們文化的一部分
Now we turn to the Old Testament
The scripture of Jewish people
It talks about the book of prophets
Especially it talks about working hard
Diligence, saving, right
Managing your money well
And managing your wealth wisely
Instead of letting nature take its course
All kinds of things that has to do with wealth
And material blessings
So Jewish people
If we understand the Old Testament
The Torah
We need to save, we need to manage our money
We need to gain and save
如果你看看猶太人的典籍
特別是舊約,有一本書叫做《針研》
你就知道裡面教很多東西都跟錢有關
我們要去勤力做事
我們要努力去賺錢
然後我們要儲錢
我們要好好管理我們的錢財
任由它荒蕩地花
這些全部都是猶太人的文化
猶太人的教導
So we know that Jesus is not against having wealth
Jesus is not against having money
Jesus is not against having material blessings
所以你不要想耶穌說
耶穌是受苦的
或者神很不喜歡我們有錢有這些祝福
Now go back to this parable
I find this something very interesting
Let me tell you how to read the Bible
How to read the story of Jesus
There is something you need to pay attention
When you come to reading some of the stories or parables told by Jesus
你看看這個故事的時候
我想你留意一件事
我想告訴你怎樣去看這些故事
這些故事很有趣的地方就是
不是比喻說了什麼才有趣
而是比喻沒有說什麼才有趣
So this is how you read the story
What is most interesting is not what the parable is saying
What is interesting is what the parable does not say
到底那個故事沒有說什麼
而它應該說的就不說
So let's think about that
Let's think about it for a moment
What is not being said in the story is the most interesting part
這個比喻沒有說的才是最有趣最值得留意的
Now remember Jesus is speaking to a Jewish society, Jewish audience
And all Jewish men believe in God
Believe in the Creator
Believe in the God of Blessing
Every Jewish man begins every morning, each morning with one prayer
And that prayer is called the Thanksgiving prayer
阿尼莫德
I give thanks
I give thanks to the God of Blessing
Every Jewish man begins every single morning when he wakes up
He prays the same prayer
I give thanks to the God of Blessing
你要知道這個故事
再提一次
就是和一個猶太人的背景聽眾說的
而我們知道每一個猶太的男人都是信創造主
救贖主和上帝是一個滿有祝福的上帝
其實每一個猶太人的男人
But if you look at this story
Alright, if you look at this story
A Jewish story
Talking about this rich guy
Never a word is attributed to God
Never a thought
think about God
So what's wrong with this guy
This guy is suffering from some sort of
You know, I guess spiritual Alzheimer
He forgets about God
Never talk about God
Never thought about Him
With all the material blessings
But somewhere up there
There's a higher power who grant me all these things
這個就是最有趣的地方
就是那個故事
說到這個男人的時候
他想都沒有想過上帝
他提都沒有提過上帝
他有很多很多的東西
越來越多
他的田產越來越多
他賺到的錢
但他從來沒有想過
原來在生命裡面
有一個更高的存在
一個上帝
在上面祝福他
來供應他一些這樣的東西
So Jesus is not against wealth
Jesus is not against having money
He is not against wise management of our resources
especially our financial resources
Jesus is poking fun of something
When you receive tons of blessing
With extra money in your pocket
And then you have no thought of
There has to be a being up there
Granting us all this
Providing us
And sustaining us
所以耶穌沒有說受苦
你千萬不要覺得整本聖經
就是不喜歡我們有錢
不喜歡我們賺錢
耶穌絕對告訴我們
我們應該要好好做管家
好好管理我們的錢
但財主給予故事
有趣的地方就在這裡
就是有錢的沒有想過
原來上面有一個上帝
我的生命是由他來sustain
我的生命是由他來供應
而不是
你從17-19的故事來看
你看看17-19
這個有錢的人對自己說什麼
這是富家子弟對自己說
他說了五次
我會
我會做這個
我會把我的田割下來
我會建造更大的
我會存放我的寶物
我會開設銀行帳戶
我會開設投資帳戶
我會告訴自己
我種了很多好東西
你看看他說了什麼
他說我的田產多豐富
我要做什麼
我要拆我的倉庫
我要開多個帳戶
我要開多個投資戶口
我要收藏我所有的東西
然後對我的靈魂說
你不需要擔心
他說了我的農產
我的果子
我的農場
我的財產
甚至我的靈魂
我的靈魂
我的倉庫
我的生命
每樣東西都是我
我 我 我 還是我呢
我想這就是聖經的主題
主要的問題不是富有
不是恭喜發財
當然神想讓你發財
神想祝福你
主要的問題不是富有
主要的問題是我們的態度
對於富有
我們的態度對於錢
而耶穌想要的是這個
最主要的問題在哪裡
不是財富問題
而是我們對財富的心態
你拿著錢
我們儲著錢
到底我們的心態是怎樣去看它呢
這是第十五節
耶穌說什麼呢
耶穌說
祂說
注意
對於財富
我出生在香港
我十歲的時候
我跟隨我的父母
去見一個家庭
一個大家庭
所有的叔叔阿姨一起
所以中國新年最好的事情
對於一個十歲的小孩來說
最好的事情是什麼呢
就是你得到錢
你得到紅包
你得到很多現金
我們有很多現金
我非常開心
我記得我得到五、六百元現金
從豆禮士
恭喜發財
當我說恭喜發財的時候
有錢進入我的口袋
這是十歲的最好的事情
我們去見他
我們一起吃飯
我們吃得很豐盛
然後叔叔阿姨
特別是叔叔
叔叔阿姨叫了所有小孩
家裡有很多小孩
來玩個遊戲
遊戲叫做魚、蝦和蝦
你玩過這個遊戲吧
我們全部豆禮士
十歲的小孩當然很開心
我記得那次
我自己有五、六百元
然後叔叔阿姨叫我們玩魚蝦蟹
我們小孩當然是玩
我們這麼多錢都玩魚蝦蟹
誰做莊
那個叔叔做莊
我們在玩的時候
我們很開心
有輸有贏
玩這個遊戲很有趣
但這遊戲很糟糕
為什麼
我們玩了一場魚蝦蟹
我們很享受
但最後我們輸光了所有錢
我們輸光了所有錢
我們輸光了所有錢包
他們都去哪了
他們都回到叔叔那裡
那是一個邪惡的叔叔
那個叔叔原來是哄我們玩
搶光我們的錢
我從來沒有試過在人生裡
有一個這樣的時刻
我們覺得人真的很邪惡
你給我們錢
沒有條件給我們錢
我們會發財
但他把所有錢都拿回來了
但在那時候
我才明白了義氣和慈悲的分別
還有我的看法
在於富貴
耶穌說什麼
他說
你要謹慎自守
免得一切的貪心
因為人的生命不在乎
家道豐富
耶穌警告他的徒弟們
要注意
要超越神
對付所有的義氣
因為人的生命不在乎
家道豐富
那是義氣和慈悲的分別呢
貪和慷慨到底有什麼分別呢
我想給你們一些想法
我想給你們兩句話
讓你們去想一想
貪和慷慨到底是什麼呢
我想我們在座中間
沒有誰說自己會貪的
我們不是貪
我們只是省錢
義氣和謙虛的分別是什麼呢
我覺得耶穌定義義氣和謙虛的分別是
義氣是關於為自己而獲得的
而謙虛和謙虛是關於為別人而獲得的
貪婪是什麼呢
就是只為自己團職
懂得感恩或者慷慨
懂得去祝福其他人
這就是義氣和謙虛和謙虛的巨大分別
有些事要想一想
義氣是關於提高自己的生活標準
而謙虛是關於提高自己的獻祭標準
貪婪就是只想提高自己的生活水準
感恩和慷慨就是提高自己的施與標準
生活標準和獻祭標準
有些事要想一想
神給我們很多東西
有意圖讓我們分享和祝福別人
特別是那些真的需要
特別是他的國王工作
上帝祝福我們很多東西
其實想我們做什麼呢
不是想我們團職
而是想我們分享和祝福其他人
特別是祝福他的工作
我兩年前就讀了一本新研究
《學術學院》
它講述了父母
把孩子養大
把孩子養大有感恩心
有感恩心
有慷慨心
這本研究的題目是
"感恩父母養大感恩孩子"
這引起了我的注意
是一本研究關於如何把六到九歲的孩子養大
如何幫助他們發展感恩心
這是兩年前報告出來的科學研究
科學研究是說
家長如何養大孩子
特別是六到九歲的孩子
如何培養孩子有種德性
有種本性
他們懂得感恩
懂得慷慨
裡面有一樣東西是他講到的
他說
"Greater parent gratitude and family religious involvement"
"were the only significant predictors"
"of more frequent parent-reported child gratitude behavior"
父母有感恩的父母
懂得感恩的父母
還有他們對信仰的投入
生活的投入
整家生活的投入
是唯一能夠預測到
就是孩子會觀察到他有感恩的行為
我們知道孩子
他們可以說謝謝
但不代表
他們說謝謝
當他們收到某些東西
但他們不代表
感恩不是說謝謝
感恩是比喻好態度更重要
你得到某些東西
你說謝謝
感恩是更重要的
感恩是對你的心
而不是只是外在的行為
說謝謝
去感恩
不是純粹說謝謝
我們知道感恩是從心裡發出來
孩子懂得說謝謝
但他未必心裡真的在說謝謝
我發現這份研究很有趣
它談到"Role Model"
"Spiritual involvement of parents, adults"
"We are happy in simple things"
"We are happy to volunteer"
"We are happy to give, to share"
"All these have great impact on our next generation"
"There is a family culture of giving instead of getting"
"That heavily impacts our children"
我覺得很有意思
你想想
當我們成為成人
當我們成為父母
我們懂得去感恩
我們懂得去慷慨
懂得去施與的時候
懂得去跟別人分享的時候
這就是我們家庭的文化
我們的家庭文化
是跟我們下一代有很大的影響
這就帶來耶穌在《事實》中說的
他說
The Lord Jesus said
It is more blessed to give than to receive
聖經記載了耶穌說了一句話
他說"施比受更為有福"
真的有Blessing的人
真的有祝福的人
是那些願意施與多過願意去接受
這是我第一段信息
第二段
應用部分
就在午餐後
我想在這裡暫停
我先說一句話
我們的教會正在建造和種植
是因為所有的人
他們貢獻
他們捐獻
他們捐錢
他們幫助
這是一家人的慈悲
這是一家人的感激
我們想繼續這樣
我們已經三年了
我們看到了很多的福音
神邀請我們成為更好的管理員
祂所給予的東西
所有的物質和福音
是神給予的
我們如何看待它們
如何處理它們
我們會否只為自己而獲得
還是我們學會了給予
就像神給予我們很多
我們成會已經三年了
在我們開始的時候到現在
我聽到很多這樣的故事
就是一些感恩
願意施比受更為有福的故事
我們教會
神的工作可以繼續延伸
完全是因為這些故事
新年流流
恭喜發財之餘
我們希望大家能夠多一點祝福
但最重要的是我們如何在神面前
活得更加豐盛
施比受更為有福
在上帝眼中做一個有福的人
我想展示給大家一個影片
這個影片是為了介紹
2019年的新的管理員
等一下我們有一個短片
我想用這個短片來介紹
我們新的管理員
我們教會的領袖
我們選出來的領袖
我想請大家想像這個影片
是一個邀請
並不是只關於知道誰是誰
但這個影片是一個邀請
給所有人
每一個人
我們想想如何建立教會
我們想想如何一起服務
我們想想如何活得更加豐盛
更加豐盛的禮物
比得到的更豐盛
看過影片的時候想一想
到底我們除了認識這些叫團成員
這些舊的領袖之外
我們想一想
我們如何可以在上帝給我們這麼多祝福的時候
我們做一個好的管家
施比受更為有福